A Guide to the Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial records, James Cannon, Series 7 FA356
Rockefeller Archive Center
Nelson A. Rockefeller gubernatorial records, James Cannon, Series 7
1968-1971
Rockefeller Archive Center
Boyd, Joseph H.
New York (State). State Commission for Human Rights
New York (State). Governor (1959-1973: Rockefeller)
Whitman, Ann
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
Morrow, Hugh
New York (State). Dept. of Civil Service
Ronan, William J. (William John)
Cannon, James M.
FA356
17 box(es)
Biographical/Historical note
Nelson A. Rockefeller served as governor of New York from January 1, 1959, to December 18, 1973. He was the first person elected to four consecutive four-year terms as a state governor.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 15 7
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for scholarly research, except where particular restrictions are noted.
RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
Arrangement note
This series is divided into two subseries:
Subseries 1 - Revenue Sharing, 1971-1972 Subseries 2 - Latin American Mission, 1968-1972
Other Finding Aids note
Detailed finding aids for each series of this collection are available:
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Appointments Office (FA353)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Assembly and Senate Memos (FA354)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Joseph H. Boyd (FA355)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Affirmative Action (N. Lee Cook) (FA357)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Counsel's Office (FA358)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, New York State Committee to Reelect the President (FA359)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Jerry A. Danzig (FA360)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Executive Chamber (FA361)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, 55th Street (FA362)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Issue Books (FA363)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Arthur Massolo (FA364)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Hugh Morrow (FA242)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, New York Office (FA365)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Civil Service Resolutions (Charles H. Palmer) (FA366)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Political Files (FA367)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Press Office (FA368)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Public Relations (FA369)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Departmental Reports (FA370)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, William J. Ronan (FA371)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Speeches (FA372)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Diane Van Wie (FA373)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Ann C. Whitman, Gubernatorial (FA374)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Gene Wyckoff (FA375)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, New York Republican State Fund Raising Reports (FA376)
Scope and Contents note
NOTE TO RESEARCHERS
This series contains the office files of James Cannon. They document official activities in the execution of his duties as a member of Nelson A. Rockefeller's staff. The actions, decisions, and exchanges of information or points of view documented here occurred in the course of proposing and implementing policies for the Rockefeller administration, political campaigns, and/or Rockefeller's personal activities. However, unless a document is specifically addressed to or from Rockefeller, or is referred to in a document addressed to him, it should not be assumed he saw the document or was aware of its existence or substance. Furthermore, researchers should bear in mind that staff files may contain documents or drafts addressed to Rockefeller that were never shown to him.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
This series contains a portion of the files of James Cannon. They were created primarily during Cannon's tenure as an executive assistant to Governor Nelson Rockefeller. Cannon worked in the New York State Washington Office in the early 1970s and reported on fiscal and revenue sharing matters in the U.S. Congress. In 1969, Cannon was part of the Governor's staff on the Presidential Mission to Latin America.
Arms control -- United States; Arms control; Affirmative action programs -- New York (State); Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1970; Human rights; International economic relations; International relations; International relations -- United States; Latin America; Legislation -- New York (State); New York (N.Y.); New York (State); Political campaigns -- United States; Political science; Presidential campaigns -- United States; United States; Vice-Presidents -- United States; Public relations; State governments -- United States; Presidential candidates -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Public policy; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1962; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1966; Government policy; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Economics; Federal government -- United States; Civil service; Civil service -- New York (State); Civil defense; Civil defense -- United States; Boyd, Joseph H.; New York (State). State Commission for Human Rights; New York (State). Governor (1959-1973: Rockefeller); Whitman, Ann; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich); Morrow, Hugh; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); New York (State). Dept. of Civil Service; Ronan, William J. (William John); Cannon, James M.
- Revenue Sharing, 1971-1972; 1; 4 document box(es)
  Scope and Contents note
  This subseries primarily concerns Cannon's tenure in Washington, DC, where he attended to fiscal matters before the U.S. Congress on behalf of Governor Rockefeller. Cannon served as a intermediary representing the interests of the Rockefeller administration to the members of the New York State Congressional Delegation. The chronological files that start the subseries deal with the events and circumstances leading up to the passage of the State and Local Fiscal Assistance Act of 1972. Of note in the subseries is Folder 18, which concerns the General Grant Revenue Act of 1971, proposed by New York Congressmen Hugh Carey and Ed Koch.
  - Chronological Files - September 1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Press releases, correspondence on congressional action on HR 14370, the State and Local Fiscal Assistance Act of 1972.
  - Chronological Files - October 1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chronological Files - December 1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chronological Files - February 1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chronological Files - February/March 1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chronological Files - April 1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chronological Files - May 1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chronological Files - House of Representatives, June 1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Tally sheets on closed rule votes, correspondence with members of New York State congressional delegation, notes on Members of Congress.
  - Chronological Files - Senate, June-July 1972 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Charts, reports, legislation from U. S. Senate Finance Committee, testimony, press releases, clippings on bill.
  - Chronological Files - Senate, June-July 1972 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Chronological Files - July 1972 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Chronological Files - August 1972 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Subject Files - Background Materials (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Revenue sharing general files, bound volumes on government finance.
  - Subject Files - Background Materials (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Subject Files - "Big Six Mayors", May 1971 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Correspondence with mayors of the six largest cities in New York (Albany, Buffalo, New York, Rochester, Syracuse, and Yonkers) on revenue sharing plans and the impact on their cities.
  - Subject Files - Byrnes Statement, April 1972 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Statement by Representative John W. Byrnes (R-WI) on HR 14370; text of HR 14370.
  - Subject Files - Byrnes Tax Credit Proposal, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Correspondence and memoranda on alternative plan proposed by Congressman Byrnes offering tax credits as a form of revenue sharing.
  - Subject Files - Carey-Koch Bill, May 1971 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Correspondence and memoranda on the General Grant Revenue Act of 1971, proposed by Congressman Hugh Carey and Congressman Edward Koch.
  - Subject Files - Charts, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Table 2, State and Local Taxes as a percentage of personal income by states; Table 3, General Revenue from other sources as a percentage of personal income by states; Table 8, Intergovernmental Expenditures/State Aid related to population, personal income and state general expenditures by states; Table 9, State Government Taxes as a percentage of total state and local government taxes.
  - Subject Files - "Congressional Record" Comments, Favorable, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Copies of pages from the "Congressional Record" supporting revenue sharing proposals.
  - Subject Files - HR 14370 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    Copy of text of HR 14370 on revenue sharing, April 17, 1972.
  - Subject Files - Meeting with President Nixon, June 1971 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Notes, schedules, correspondence, memoranda on meeting in Rochester, New York between NAR and President Nixon on revenue sharing.
  - Subject Files - Mills Visit, April 1972 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Correspondence, memoranda, schedules for visit by Congressman Wilbur Mills to New York State.
  - Subject Files - Mills Visit, April 1972 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Subject Files - Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Loose, unfiled papers on revenue sharing.
  - Subject Files - Other Governors Letters and Statements, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    Letters, press releases from governors on revenue sharing issues.
  - Subject Files - Report, 1 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    Analyses of revenue sharing issues, comparison of different plans.
  - Subject Files - Report, 2 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Subject Files - Revenue Sharing, Special, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    General Information
  - Subject Files - Revenue Sharing, Special, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    Badillo, HR 7367, Intergovernmental Emergency Advance Act of 1971
  - Subject Files - Revenue Sharing, Special, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    Daniels, HR 3613, Emergency Employment Act of 1971
  - Subject Files - Revenue Sharing, Special - Education, 1968-1971 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    Appropriations bill for education in United States.
  - Subject Files - Revenue Sharing, Special, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    Reuss, HR 7594, State and Metropolitan Development Act of 1971
  - Subject Files - Talking Points (Box 3, Folder 34)
    Issues for NAR to emphasize on HR 14370.
  - Subject Files - Testimony, General, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    Transcript, press releases of NAR testimony on revenue sharing.
  - Subject Files - Testimony, James M. Cannon Notes (Box 3, Folder 36)
    Cannon's handwritten notes on testimony before committees.
  - Subject Files - Testimony, NAR, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    NAR's testimony on revenue sharing before the U.S. House Ways and Means Committee, June 15, 1971.
  - Subject Files - Testimony, Ways and Means, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    Transcripts, press releases of NAR's and others' testimony on revenue sharing before the U.S. House Ways and Means Committee.
  - Subject Files - Testimony, Ways and Means, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Subject Files - Testimony, Ways and Means Members, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    Correspondence with members of Congress on revenue sharing issues before Congress.
  - Subject Files - Welfare - HR 1, January 1972 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    Correspondence, memoranda, testimony on Welfare Reform Bill, January 1972.
  - Subject Files - Welfare - HR 1, January 1972 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Subject Files - Welfare - Rep. Carey, HR 5379, Amending Social Security Act, March 1971 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    Testimony before the U.S. House.
  - Subject Files - Welfare - Rep. Green, HR 7249, April 1971 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    Amending Social Security Act to include additional family assistance. Testimony before the U.S. House.
  - Subject Files - Welfare - Sen. Hartke, S 1162, March 1971 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    Permit states and local governments to increase taxes to offer tax credits; testimony before the U. S. Senate.
  - Subject Files - Welfare - Rep. Ullman, HR 6004, March 1971 (Box 4, Folder 46)
    Rehabilitation Employee Assistance and Child Care Act of [March] 1971. Testimony before the U. S. House.
- Latin American Mission, 1968-1972; 2; 13 document box(es)
  After several discussions with President Richard Nixon, in 1969 Nelson Rockefeller was appointed to undertake a Presidential Mission to Latin America to consult with the leaders of those republics and determine the needs and conditions there. During the spring and summer of that year, Rockefeller toured 20 Latin American countries. This subseries contains a small sample of the documentation of the mission. Notable in this subseries is correspondence with members of President Nixon's staff, specifically National Security Advisor Henry Kissinger, who monitored the mission from Washington.
  Related Archival Materials note
  Additional extensive materials on the Latin American Mission may be found in the Washington, DC, series in Record Group 4 of the Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers (Boxes 98-201).
  - Country files
    Correspondence, memoranda, notes, clippings, schedules, background information, telexes to Henry Kissinger at White House, memos from Kissinger, correspondence with Berent Friele, transcripts and remarks, and meeting notes.
    - Argentina, 1968-1970 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Argentina - Briefing Book, 1968-1970 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - Argentina - Briefing Book, 1968-1970 (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - Barbados, 1968-1970 (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - Barbados - Briefing Book, 1968-1970 (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - Bolivia, 1968-1970 (Box 5, Folder 52)
    - Bolivia - Briefing Book, 1968-1970 (Box 5, Folder 53)
    - Brazil, 1968-1970 (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - Brazil, 1968-1970 (Box 6, Folder 55)
    - Brazil, 1968-1970 (Box 6, Folder 56)
    - Brazil, 1968-1970 (Box 6, Folder 57)
    - Brazil - Briefing Book, 1968-1970 (Box 6, Folder 58)
    - Brazil - Briefing Book, 1968-1970 (Box 6, Folder 59)
    - Brazil - Report, Brazilian Educational Radio and TV Experiment, July 1968 (Box 7, Folder 60)
    - Brazil - Report, "Projecto Saci, Parte I", May 1968 (Box 7, Folder 61)
    - Brazil - Report, "Projecto Saci, Parte II", May 1968 (Box 7, Folder 62)
    - Brazil - Report, "Projecto Saci, Parte III", May 1968 (Box 7, Folder 63)
    - Central American Common Market, 1968-1972 (Box 7, Folder 64)
    - Central American Common Market - Briefing Book, 1968-1972 (Box 7, Folder 65)
    - Chile, 1968-1972 (Box 7, Folder 66)
    - Chile - Briefing Book, 1968-1972 (Box 7, Folder 67)
    - Haiti, 1968-1972 (Box 7, Folder 68)
    - Haiti - Briefing Book, 1968-1972 (Box 7, Folder 69)
    - Honduras, 1968-1972 (Box 8, Folder 70)
    - Honduras - Briefing Book, 1968-1972 (Box 8, Folder 71)
    - Jamaica, 1968-1972 (Box 8, Folder 72)
    - Jamaica - Briefing Book, 1968-1972 (Box 8, Folder 73)
    - Mexico, 1968-1972 (Box 8, Folder 74)
    - Mexico, 1968-1972 (Box 8, Folder 75)
    - Mexico, 1968-1972 (Box 8, Folder 76)
    - Mexico - Briefing Book, 1968-1972 (Box 9, Folder 77)
    - Nicaragua, 1968-1972 (Box 9, Folder 78)
    - Nicaragua - Briefing Book, 1968-1972 (Box 9, Folder 79)
    - Panama, 1968-1972 (Box 9, Folder 80)
    - Panama, 1968-1972 (Box 9, Folder 81)
    - Panama - Briefing Book, 1968-1972 (Box 9, Folder 82)
    - Uruguay, 1968-1972 (Box 10, Folder 83)
    - Uruguay, 1968-1972 (Box 10, Folder 84)
    - Uruguay - Briefing Book, 1968-1972 (Box 10, Folder 85)
    - Venezuela, 1968-1972 (Box 10, Folder 86)
    - Venezuela - Briefing Book, 1968-1972 (Box 10, Folder 87)
    - Venezuela - Briefing Book, 1968-1972 (Box 10, Folder 88)
    - Country Reports, 1968-1972 (Box 11, Folder 89)
    - Country Reports, 1968-1972 (Box 11, Folder 90)
    - Country Reports, 1968-1972 (Box 11, Folder 91)
    - Country Reports, 1968-1972 (Box 11, Folder 92)
    - General Information, 1968-1972 (Box 11, Folder 93)
  - Advance (Box 12, Folder 94)
    Memos on details of trip.
  - Agency for International Development (USAID) (Box 12, Folder 95)
    Correspondence from the U. S. Agency for International Development on changes in status of Latin American affairs.
  - Art Treaty (Box 12, Folder 96)
    Correspondence and memoranda on treaty signed regarding illegal trafficking in Latin American art objects.
  - Briefings, Council on Foreign Relations (Box 12, Folder 97)
    Materials from discussion group to assist with mission issues; position papers.
  - Cables (Box 12, Folder 98)
    Copies of cables and telegrams to and from U.S. embassies and consulates on Mission items.
  - Cables (Box 12, Folder 98A)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Restricted material
  - China Study (Box 12, Folder 99)
    Lloyd Free report on China, sent to NAR by Free in 1971 coinciding with President Nixon's visit to China.
  - Church in Latin America (Box 12, Folder 100)
    Uncredited, undated, expansive report on "Subversion of the Church in Latin America."
  - Comments on NAR/Latin American Policy (Box 12, Folder 101)
    Telexes, clippings, notes on reaction to the mission.
  - Congressional Relations (Box 12, Folder 102)
    Correspondence and memoranda on Latin American affairs with members of the U. S. Congress; invitations to NAR to speak before committees; legislation on Latin American development programs.
  - Drafts
    Sections of Report to the President on the Mission.
    - Agriculture (Box 13, Folder 103)
    - U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID) (Box 13, Folder 104)
    - CECLA (Special Latin American Coordinating Committee) (Box 13, Folder 105)
    - Conservation (Box 13, Folder 106)
    - Culture (Box 13, Folder 107)
    - Education (Box 13, Folder 108)
    - Finance and Economics (Box 13, Folder 109)
    - Fishing (Box 13, Folder 110)
    - General Readings (Box 13, Folder 111)
      Cannon notes, memos to NAR on U.S. military aid program in Latin America, reports.
    - Government Structure (Box 13, Folder 112)
      Memoranda, correspondence, reports on effective use of U.S. resources in support of the Inter-American System (IAS).
    - Health (Box 14, Folder 113)
    - Information (Box 14, Folder 114)
    - Inter-American System (IAS) (Box 14, Folder 115)
      Notes, reports, memoranda on strengths and weaknesses of the IAS.
    - Labor (Box 14, Folder 116)
    - Miscellaneous Draft Notes (Box 14, Folder 117)
      Staff member observations, correspondence, memoranda on suggested report contents.
    - Notes by James Cannon from meeting, August 12, 1969 (Box 14, Folder 118)
    - Notes by James Cannon from meeting, August 13, 1969 (Box 14, Folder 119)
    - Outline (Box 14, Folder 120)
      Suggested outline and chapter headings.
    - Preamble (Box 14, Folder 121)
    - Private Enterprise (Box 14, Folder 122)
    - Recognition (Box 14, Folder 123)
      Legislation, congressional record of U.S. Senate action of recognizing foreign governments.
    - Recommendations (Box 14, Folder 124)
    - Rural Development (Box 15, Folder 125)
    - Science and Technology (Box 15, Folder 126)
    - Section I - Foreword written by NAR (Box 15, Folder 127)
    - Section II (Box 15, Folder 128)
      Draft of section, recommendations on direction and policy.
    - Security (Box 15, Folder 129)
    - Technical Assistance (Box 15, Folder 130)
    - Trade (Box 15, Folder 131)
    - Urban Affairs (Box 15, Folder 132)
    - Women (Box 15, Folder 133)
    - Work with People (Box 15, Folder 134)
  - Foreign Aid (Box 16, Folder 135)
    Information on U.S. aid to Latin American countries; clippings on mission.
  - Foreign Policy Speech (Box 16, Folder 136)
    Notes and transcript of NAR foreign policy speech, delivered at the National Press Club, October 31, 1972.
  - General (Box 16, Folder 137)
    Miscellaneous materials, clippings, memoranda and correspondence.
  - Invitations (Box 16, Folder 138)
    Offers to NAR to speak or appears at events relating to the mission.
  - Letters to Heads of State, February 19, 1969 (Box 16, Folder 139)
    Introductory letters to Latin American leaders in advance of visit.
  - Letters to Ambassadors, March 31, 1969 (Box 16, Folder 140)
    Preparatory letter to U. S. Ambassadors and Charge D'affaires in countries to be visited by NAR.
  - Letters to Heads of State, Follow-Up, April 1969 (Box 16, Folder 141)
    Follow-up letters to leaders with expected dates of visit to their countries.
  - Major Questions (Box 16, Folder 142)
    Suggested topics for consideration on mission offered by academic and private individuals.
  - Mission Reports and Recommendations (Box 16, Folder 143)
    Memo from Cannon on behalf of NAR calling for final drafts from mission staff.
  - Nixon Memos (Box 16, Folder 144)
    Drafts of memos to President Nixon proposing the Latin American Mission; correspondence and memoranda on mission related issues; NAR notes, draft of memo.
  - Outline (Box 17, Folder 145)
    July 1969 memorandum with outline of report to president.
  - People to be Seen by NAR (Box 17, Folder 146)
    Correspondence and memoranda on individuals for NAR to consult with on trip issues.
  - Pocantico Working Session, July 1969 (Box 17, Folder 147)
    Mission staff meeting held at Kykuit, July 1969, on report drafting.
  - Post-Trip Material (Box 17, Folder 148)
    Correspondence and memoranda on public relations events attended by NAR on Latin American Mission.
  - Press (Box 17, Folder 149)
    Clippings and press releases on mission.
  - Press Material (Box 17, Folder 150)
    Correspondence and memoranda on suggested members of the press to be included in the mission.
  - "Read" File (Box 17, Folder 151)
    Miscellaneous materials forwarded for NAR to read.
  - "Read" File (Box 17, Folder 152)
  - Schedules (Box 17, Folder 153)
    Planned schedules for Latin American Mission.
  - Transcripts of NAR Remarks (Box 17, Folder 154)
    Copies of NAR remarks on a variety of issues, September-November 1972.